{
  "reference_number": "2026",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a goal to reach net zero emissions by the second half of the century and the Climate Change Commission advises on the specific target for the Government to set later",
      "answer_index": 11,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Carbon Dioxide - Reducing net carbon dioxide emissions to zero by 2050",
      "answer_index": 13,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions (including from new forest planting) and using some emissions reductions from overseas (international carbon units) that have strong environmental safeguards",
      "answer_index": 2,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Circumstances change, so while a goal must be worked towards, the day to day has to be flexible."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Any plans must be just and changes need to bear on all New Zealanders in balance to their means and needs."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Advice is simply not enough - there has to be a way to prevent political subversion of advice."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Climate change is happening now: not adapting to something that is actually occurring would be an epic act of denial!"
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Our adaptation to climate change has to be collaborative to be maximally effective and could pave the way for greater collaboration in\nthe public sector response to climate change in general."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I would urge those constructing legislation to consider the following when drafting the bill on carbon emissions. That just change be\nthe core principle of legislation and practice. Changes need to bear on all New Zealanders in balance to their means and needs. To\n\ndo anything other than equitably reward useful behaviour and control poor practices strikes at the very heart of our democracy. That\nthe commission, and public confidence, be protected. To protect the public confidence, it is necessary to use transparent processes\n\nand create an entirely independent public watchdog, that has a legislated obligation to investigate and ‘whistle-blow’, when attempts\nare made to subvert the commission’s work. That independence of thought and action is guaranteed. Governments change and so,\ntherefore, do priorities, policy and ways of working. Any commissioners or other body need to be independent of political and normal\n\nadministrative structures to remain apolitical. That there is a requirement to seek causes rather than symptoms. An illustrative\nexample: transport is a major carbon emitter. Shifting the vehicle fleet to electric vehicles merely treats a symptom, where being\nprepared to remedy cause by redeveloping our cities to low-carbon, sustainable, more productive, more liveable forms. Working on\n\ncauses is much harder, but necessary. That our legislators and administrators not be proud. That it be mandated that advice be\nactively sought from outside New Zealand on technologies and methods. We need to be able to learn from other people’s successes\n\nand mistakes. That the wisdom of contrarian views are considered. Some caution is needed with some of the technologies becoming\navailable and a very critical assessment is vital. Being first with something like a heavy uptake in battery technology that might swiftly\nbe made obsolete by hydrogen-based energy storage would be very unwise. That courage be a requirement. The moral courage to\n\nenact necessary measures that may be unpopular is going to be needed, as well as the practical ability to withstand the assaults of\nspecial interest groups and changing government’s priorities. Both of those need to be somehow built in to legislation. That the\n\nneed for great change is accepted. The changes required have the potential to put New Zealand on what is effectively an emergency\nfooting and may, at times, require extraordinary measures. That plain speaking – in all languages - be required.\n\n\n\n\n You have elected to withhold your personal details from publication."
    }
  ]
}
